<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">The Heart's Rocketeers</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io" />
<updated>2016-06-03T19:12:52+02:00</updated>
<id>https://therocketeers.github.io/</id>
<author>
  <name>James Powell</name>
  <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io/</uri>
  <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Fortress]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/pushkin/the-fortress/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/pushkin/the-fortress</id>
  <published>2016-05-17T12:54:38+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-17T12:54:38+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;The Belogorsk fortress was situated at a distance of forty 
versts from Orenburg. The road lay along the steep bank of the 
Yaik. The river was not yet frozen over, and its leaden current
showed dark and dreary between the monotonous snow-covered
banks. ON either side stretched the Kirghisz steppe. I was plunged 
in meditation, for the greaer part melancholy. Garrison life
held few attractions for me. I tried to imagine what Captain
Mironov, my future superior officer, would be like, and formed
a picture of a severe, bad-tempered old man, oblivious to all but 
the service, and ready to arrest me and put me on bread and
water for the most trivial offence. The dusk was beginning to
fall. We were driving at a fair speed. “Is it far to the fortress?”
I asked my driver. “Not very,” he replied. &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/cb/Pushkin_Alexander_by_Sokolov_P..jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Puskin at work&quot; class=&quot;wrap-around&quot; /&gt; “It’s just comming into sight, yonder.” I looked all around me, expecting to see formidable
bastions, turrets, and ramparts; but I could see nothing 
but a huddle of wooden buildings surrounded by a log fence.
On one side of the road were three or four haystacks, half-
covered with snow, on the other a tumble-down mill with idly
drooping bark sails. “Where’s the fortress?” I asked in surprise.
“There it is,” replied the driver, pointing to the hamlet into 
which we were turning at that moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the gate I saw an ancient iron cannon; the streets were narrow an crooked; the
houses low and ost of them had straw thatches. I ordered the 
driver to go on to the commandant’s office, and a minute later
the sleigh drew up befor a small wooden house, standing on 
high ground, next to a wooden church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-cats-funeral&quot;&gt;The Cat’s Funeral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody came to meet me. I went into the porch and opened
the door into the passage. An invalided soldier was perched on
a table putting a blue patch on the elbow of a green uniform. I
told him to announce my arrival. “You can go in, Sir” he 
replied. “They’re at home.” I went into a clean little room, 
furnished in the old-fashioned style. In one corner was a crockery
cupboard, on the wall hung an officer’s diploma, framed and
glazed; next to it were crude pictures representing the storming
of Kistrin and Ochakov, “The Choice of a Bride”, and “The
Cat’s Funeral”. At the window sat an old lady in a waddded
jacket with a kerchief on her head. She was winding wool which
a one-eyed ancient in officer’s uniform held up for her aroun
his outstrethced hands. “What can I do for you, Sir?” asked
the old woman going on with her occupation. I repied that I 
had come to serve in the army and considered it my duty to
report to the captian, and here I turned to the on-eyed old man,
whom I took for the commnadant. But the mistress of the house
interrupted the speech I had prepared beforehand. “Ivan Kuzmich
is out,” she said. “He had gone to visit Father Gerasim;
but it is no matter, Sir. I am his wife, an you are very welcome. 
Take a seat, Sir.” She called a servant-girl, whom she 
told to go for the sergeant. The old man observed me inquisitively
from his solitary eye. “May I venture to enquire what 
regiment you were in?” he asked. I satisfied his curiosity. “And
may I ask,” he continued, “what caused you to leave the Guards
for a garrison?” I replied that such had been the will of my 
superiors. “For conduct unworthy of an officer of the Guards
I presume,” continued my importunate interrogator. “Enough
of you prattle,” said the captain’s lady, “can’t you see the 
young man is tired from his journey - let him alone! (Hold
your hands up, do!) And you, Sir,” she went on, addressing me,
“don’t grieve at having been packed off to this out-of-the-way
spot, You’re not the first, you won’t be the last. You won’t 
mind it, after you get used to it. It’s over four years since Alexei
Ivanovich Shvabrin was transferred to us for manslaughter.
The Lord knows what made him do it; you see, he and some 
lieutenant went to the outskirts of the town, and took their
swords with them, and started prodding at each other; and
Alexei Ivanovich ran the lieutenant throught the body, and that
in the presence of two witnesses. Can’t be helped! It might 
happen to anybody.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just then the sergeant, a stalwart young Cossack, entered the 
room. “Maximich,” said the old lady, “find quarters for the
officer, clean ones.” “Yes, Vasilissa Yegorovna,” replied the 
sergeant. “Shall I quarter His Honour on Ivan Polezhaev?”
“No, no, Maximich,” said the captian’s lady. “It’s crowded
enough there as it is, but Polezhaev is my friend, and understands
that we are his superiors” Take the officer … what’s
your name, Sir? Pyotr Andreich. Take Pyotr Andreich to 
Semen Kuzov. He let his horse into my vegetable garden, the 
rascal! Well, Maximich, is everything in order?”&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/pushkin/the-fortress/&quot;&gt;The Fortress&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on May 17, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello world there]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/this-is-a-title/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/this-is-a-title</id>
  <published>2016-05-05T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;d dreary between the monotonous snow-covered banks. ON either side stretched the Kirghisz steppe. I was plunged in meditation, for the greaer part melancholy. Garrison life held few attractions for me. I tried to imagine what Captain Mironov, my future superior officer, would be like, and formed a picture of a severe, bad-tempered old man, oblivious to all but the service, and ready to arrest me and put me on bread and water for the most trivial offen&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/this-is-a-title/&quot;&gt;Hello world there&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on May 05, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[works like a charm]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/something-there-is/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/something-there-is</id>
  <published>2016-05-05T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;klashfjlskdfahjksdfjlskdhfvslakghspiahdlkfhalkzdfj&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/something-there-is/&quot;&gt;works like a charm&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on May 05, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello Dolly]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/hello-dolly/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/hello-dolly</id>
  <published>2016-05-05T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This seems like a nice way to go&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/hello-dolly/&quot;&gt;Hello Dolly&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on May 05, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[hello]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/hello/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/hello</id>
  <published>2016-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;lahdfljashfd&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/hello/&quot;&gt;hello&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on May 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello George]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/hello-george/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/hello-george</id>
  <published>2016-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This is another test post. Just see how you like it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/hello-george/&quot;&gt;Hello George&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on May 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting comfy with Jekyll]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/getting-comfy-with-jekyll/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/getting-comfy-with-jekyll</id>
  <published>2016-04-10T14:02:58+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-04-10T14:02:58+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t intend this to be a “how to” style post. If you’re unfamiliar with Jekyll and Git then you’d better leave this post alone. Try reading some of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.cr.rs/tags/&quot;&gt;other posts&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll can be a bitch if you’re new to static blogging. For starters, Jekyll does not have a shiny content editor like Wordpress or Ghost. And to be honest that’s the way I like her. But the frustrating thing about making a blog with Jekyll is the way I have to host it. Right now this blog is hosted with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; and the source code is on Github. After manually adding each post I trigger &lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.org&quot;&gt;Travis CI&lt;/a&gt; with a push to github. Travis builds and then deploys the generated code to Netlify using their api. This problem mainly stems from the fact that Netlify is a CDN (Content Delivery Network) and can only work with static files. That means no server side scripts for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get around this problem you need a minimal content editor – a place where you bring together all your different tools in one place so that they can all interact. Right now the tools I use are Github, Netlify, Travis-CI and &lt;a href=&quot;https://heroku.com&quot;&gt;Heroku&lt;/a&gt; along with &lt;a href=&quot;https://draftin.com&quot;&gt;Draft&lt;/a&gt; – a version controlled, online text editor for writers. That’s a long list and I wish I could narrow it down to a few basic tools. Barring that my only other choice was to create an app that would bring all these different tools together to create an optimized work flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script I wrote for this purpose gradually grew and became almost 500 lines of nodejs code. I call it Burlesque, because its complicated and messy. The first and major function for Burlesque was to act as a comment server. The other functions grew from this. Right now Burlesque has the ability to block spammers and to act as a Gravatar proxy server. Besides this Burlesque also has a webhook for publishing directly from Draft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these features requires a lot of explanation. You can find each of these below.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/getting-comfy-with-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Getting comfy with Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on April 10, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Travis CI to automatically deploy Jekyll on Netlify]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/using-travis-ci-to-deploy-jekyll-on-netlify/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/using-travis-ci-to-deploy-jekyll-on-netlify</id>
  <published>2016-03-06T16:35:57+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-03-06T16:35:57+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I recently moved my website from Github pages to Netlify. The reason I did this was because Netlify provides free static hosting through a worldwide CDN or in other words through a content delivery network. As a result my website is now blazingly fast anywhere around the world. Netlify CDN automatically optimizes my website resources so that they can be downloaded faster. Netlify is also convenient as it supports continuous integration which meant each time I made some modification and pushed to Github my site is automatically regenerated and deployed. Moving to Netlify also meant that I could use an SSL certificate with my custom domain for free. How cool is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I write this post is that soon after I moved to Netlify I noticed that there was a build counter on their console that recorded how many times my site had been deployed and this build counter was red and perilously close to the 50 build mark. A bit of nosing around made me realize that Netlify only supports 50 automatic deployments from Github a month. But manual deployments were still free. I could drag and drop my website to upload but that was about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To rectify this major inconvenience I searched around for ways to make this process as painless as possible. I finally stumbled on Travis CI. Travis CI is a continuous integration platform for developers to test their code on and was free for open source projects. But I found out that many people were using Travis CI for deploying jekyll to a variety of places. Travis CI is simple to use but the learning curve was a bit steep. I found the process very irksome since there was scarcely any resources where I could find help outside of the documentation. So I decided to write a how to style post on manually deploying to Netlify using their REST api.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-1&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some files to added and scripts to be tweaked. In the root of your repositorysitory create a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; file. This is how you let Travis know what you want to do. Leave it empty for the moment. Create a two new bash files: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;build.sh&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;deploy.sh&lt;/code&gt; in a folder named &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scripts&lt;/code&gt; in the root folder of your repository. Make sure you have your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt; setup. Edit the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt; to include two new lines, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gem &#39;jekyll&#39;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gem &#39;rake&#39;&lt;/code&gt;. Then make a file named &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Rakefile&lt;/code&gt; in your root folder and add the following code to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;task default: [:test]

task :test do
  ruby &quot;tests.rb&quot;
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now edit the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;build.sh&lt;/code&gt; file to add the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env bash&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;set&lt;/span&gt; -e &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# halt script on error&lt;/span&gt;

jekyll build
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then edit the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;deploy.sh&lt;/code&gt; file to include this code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env bash&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;set&lt;/span&gt; -e &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# halt script on error&lt;/span&gt;

zip -r website.zip _site

curl -H &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Content-Type: application/zip&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
     -H &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Authorization: Bearer &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$NETLIFYKEY&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
     --data-binary &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;@website.zip&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
     https://api.netlify.com/api/v1/sites/&amp;lt;Your site domain name&amp;gt;/deploys
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;editing-the-travisyml-file&quot;&gt;Editing the .travis.yml file&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open up the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; file you created earlier and add the following code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;language: ruby
rvm:
- 2.1

# install jekyll from gemfile
install: 
   - bundle install
   - rake
   - chmod +x ./scripts/build.sh
   - ./scripts/build.sh

# build site
scripts: true

# deploy to netlify
after_success: 
   - chmod +x ./scripts/deploy.sh
   - ./scripts/deploy.sh

# branch whitelist, only for GitHub Pages
branches:
  only:
  - master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now create a file named &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tests.rb&lt;/code&gt; in the root of your repository with the following code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;puts &quot;Captain! I&#39;m fine!&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-2&quot;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.org&quot;&gt;Travis CI&lt;/a&gt; and connect it to your Github account. Follow the instructions to activate your repository and push to Github for your first build. The build will fail, don’t worry. In your Travis CI dashboard you can find the More Options button to your right. The settings for your repository will be there. In your settings page you have the option to add new environment variables. Setting up an environment variable enable you to access that variable in your bash script. Before you create an environmental variable you must create a Netlify personal access token for yourself. You can get the personal access token from &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.netlify.com/applications&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Make sure to keep it safe. !!!Not in your repository!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a new environment variable called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NETLIFYKEY&lt;/code&gt; and set it to the value of the personal access token.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make some new changes to your site and push to Github and see the magic happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;explanation&quot;&gt;Explanation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travis essentially gives us a command line so that we can work with it. The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; file is used to indicate which scripts have to be run. First &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle install&lt;/code&gt; is run so that we have all our dependencies install. The rakefile is just there because Travis runs &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec rake&lt;/code&gt; automatically and we’d get an error if we didn’t have some thing in it. Each shell script we run must be made executable with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;chmod +x&lt;/code&gt; command. Then the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;./&lt;/code&gt; command runs the shell script. The first script &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;build.sh&lt;/code&gt; runs the command &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll build&lt;/code&gt; to generate your site into a folder called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt;. The second script is run only if we have a successful build. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;deploy.sh&lt;/code&gt; first takes the content of the folder &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; and then compresses it to make a zipped file &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;website.zip&lt;/code&gt;. Then we use cURL to take this file and deploy it to Netlify using their REST API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;security-concerns&quot;&gt;Security Concerns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update fixed this&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, I think you shouldn’t use the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;deploy.sh&lt;/code&gt; script if you’re hosting your source code on a public Github repositorysitory. As you can see, you have a personal access token in that file and anyone can read it since it’s on a public repository. I am currently trying to work around this problem by using gpg encryption. I’ll post updates as I go along. I you have an idea that’ll help me email me at jamespowell.auth@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;update&quot;&gt;!Update!&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I solved the security problem caused by keeping the key on your public repository by using environment variables. If you included the personal access token in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;deploy.sh&lt;/code&gt; file make sure to change it to the above. !!!And make sure that you permanently delete any previous commits that includes this change from your repository.!!!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/using-travis-ci-to-deploy-jekyll-on-netlify/&quot;&gt;Using Travis CI to automatically deploy Jekyll on Netlify&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on March 06, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing for the Web: Basic Philosophies]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/philosophy-of-the-web/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/philosophy-of-the-web</id>
  <published>2016-03-03T16:35:57+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-03-03T16:35:57+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ere are my basic philosophy for writing on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drum out whatever comes to your mind first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never delete anything you type. Leave editing for later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t use auto correct.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t waste time changing configuration. Just write. This means not changing themes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never read the comments. Better still, just disable them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disable page views and Google Analytics. Readers just come. There’s nothing more to it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never write for money or for commercial advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be outrageous. Hold nothing back. The web isn’t the place to be politically correct.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/philosophy-of-the-web/&quot;&gt;Writing for the Web: Basic Philosophies&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on March 03, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Science Behind Saving Matt Damon]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/science-behind-saving-matt-damon/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/science-behind-saving-matt-damon</id>
  <published>2016-02-27T22:44:37+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-27T22:44:37+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dcap&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;idley Scott does it again. That’s literally the only thing I can think of right now after I’ve finished watching the movie, the Martian. I thought Alien was an amazing movie but the Martian is definitely better. I was suspicious that it was one of those dump, soulless CGI movies and didn’t bother to catch it at the theater. Bad decision. Scott is one of those rare directors who can take anything and make it into a one of a kind movie you’ll remember for ever. Oh yeah, five years from now I’ll remember the Martian alright, not Gravity. Just so I won’t forget anything let me write down the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt Damon gets left behind on Mars after a storm descends on the Aries 3 mission site and threatens to tip over the MAV (Mars Ascent Vehicle). The rest of the six member crew jettisons out leaving Matt for dead. Matt is still alive but the communications antenna has broken off and pierced his suit, wounding him and destroying the biometry sensors. But it also plugs the tear in his suit, saving his life. Matt must learn to survive till the crew of Aries 4 gets there four years later. He grows food inside the hab by bringing in Mars soil and using dehydrated human excreta as manure. Matt is a botanist and he knows that you need 40 liters of water to farm a cubic meter of soil, he finds some potatoes they’d set aside for thanksgiving and uses those as seed to grow more potatoes. To get the needed water he uses iridium to catalyze the decomposition of hydrazine (which is NH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;NH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) into nitrogen and hydrogen gas. Then he burns the hydrogen gas using the oxygen in the hab atmosphere to get water. He soon has food to last him for more than 900 Mars days (of 25 hours each called a sol in the movie) instead of the 400 Mars day worth of food he had with him in the hab. Around this time he reequips one of the rover from parts scavenged from the other and starts exploring. To save energy he shuts of the heater and instead uses a nuclear thermoelectric generator to heat up the rover. By this time &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt; realizes that Matt is alive from satellite pictures of the hab taken from Mars orbit. Matt finds the old pathfinder lander and brings it back to use it to communicate with Earth which he does using &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;ASCII&lt;/strong&gt; and hexadecimals. Unfortunately the hab explodes destroying the plants and leaving him just the rover for shelter. But &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt; figures a way to bring him home earlier than the Aries 4 mission by rerouting Hermes around Earth and back to Mars so that Matt can rendezvous with Hermes using the MAV from the Aries 4 mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visual effect is breathtaking and the story is compelling. The story line takes place slightly in the future where I suppose the economy is favorable enough that they got congress to fund eight Mars missions. Well, I guess Donald Trump did become the president after all. The science is so advanced that they have a near perfect oxygen and water reclaimer, two things Matt doesn’t want for. A notable absentee was a 3D printer. &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt; is using a 3D printer right now on the International Space Station&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but we don’t see one in the movie. A &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;3D&lt;/strong&gt; printer would have come in really useful. For example &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt; could just send Matt the code in on the radio, in the rover, and Matt could 3D print parts to replace the Hab airlock. &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;3D&lt;/strong&gt; printers could even print food stuff from highly condensed organic matter which would be more economical to bring along than dehydrated food stuff. Ultimately, I think if we ever got to Mars science would have progressed enough that we would have genetically altered plants that could grow on Mars with less water. It is surprising that the Hab doesn’t have plants and seeds other than those potatoes Matt found set aside for thanksgiving. That really isn’t like &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt;. Good science would mean there’d be lots of seed, plant and tiny insects and animals they’d bring along to do experiments. After all, a botanist like Matt would be ultra interested in growing plants on Mars. (Why have him otherwise?) Even otherwise &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt; might be just smart enough to pack some for eventualities like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.nasa.gov/sites/default/files/thumbnails/image/mars_0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Artists impression of a storm on Mars&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another curious thing is why they’d allow the crew to wait till even a day before a major storm. At this point &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt; wouldn’t know a lot about storms on Mars and they’d be cautions since their prediction could be totally off. They’d even seem to know just how much force was necessary to knock the MAV off its feet. It all seems very convenient or very inconvenient depending on whether you’re Ridley Scott or Matt Damon. All in all the science seems pretty solid even if its a bit shoddy now and then, like how did Vogel make a bomb in just half an hour. It would have taken Ripley’s science department at least a day to come up with that plot point. And blowing up an airlock to let the air out? Bad move. How did Commander Lewis calculate the thrust that would generate? The tear in the airlock is not cylindrical. The nozzle shape and size can influence thrust dramatically&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Ever blown up a balloon and let if loose? Besides that you’d have to know the volume of air ejected and the pressure. I mention this because Johansson even makes a prediction regarding the final distance and relative velocity at one point. I don’t know about you but I’d love to have that gal on my spaceship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt decomposes hydrazine by using an iridium catalyst to get hydrogen and nitrogen. This has some basis in reality. Monopropellant thrusters used for attitude control uses hydrazine as fuel. The decomposition of hydrazine is actually catalyzed by granular alumina coated with iridium&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In fact that what Matt uses in the movie. I been wondering how Matt got so much Iridium since iridium is very rare and expensive. But the problem is that the decompostion of hydrazine is very very exothermic (meaning it releases energy). The reaction takes place at about a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1000^{0}&lt;/script&gt; C. Besides, hydrazine decomposes to give hydrogen, oxygen and ammonia. A fact thats not mentioned in the movie. The evolved hydrogen would spontaneously react with the oxygen in the hab atmosphere but we see Matt struggling to light the hydrogen on fire. The evolved ammonia would meanwhile saturate the hab atmosphere, poisoning Matt. I’m not sure the hab life support system is designed to eliminate ammonia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funniest part of the movie is actually not even connected to the movie. Its Project Elrond. The Council of Elrond in the Lord of the Ring decides to entrust Frodo with the task of destroying the One Ring by tossing it in to Mount Doom. Guess which actor was at the Council of Elrond. Sean Bean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://cdn.pastemagazine.com/www/system/images/photo_albums/sean-bean-2/large/28-bean-lordoftherings.jpg?1384968217&quot; alt=&quot;Sean Bean does the thing with the hand.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You don’t just walk in to Mordor.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only science that just might confuse the reader is the lot of orbital maneuvering and jiggling that goes on. As far as I know the general public still thinks rocket are fired straight up into orbit. The nerds will forgive me if I err. But you see that’s not the case. I’ll take a moment to educate the general public. The faint of  heart should go no further. But it’s not that hard. It’s just rocket science after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-divider&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dcap&quot;&gt;L&lt;/span&gt;et’s define what an orbit is first. An orbit is the path of a freely falling body. Toss that pen off your desk and it follows a parabolic path to the ground. Fire a projectile and it follows a parabolic path to the enemy. A parabola is not quite a circle nor it is it a straight line. Parabolas are actually a class of curves of the second order. The first order being straight lines. Believe it or not circles are related to the parabola or more exactly to its cousin, the ellipse. When you start throwing a body faster and faster parallel to the ground, after a certain point the parabola traces out the curvature of the Earth and it goes on forever around the Earth. Not really. Friction from the atmosphere would slow it down and it would hit the earth a few miles away. But if you get high enough, say a hundred kilometers, you’re high enough so that there’s not much air left and an orbit is possible. This time instead of a parabola the path traced is an ellipse – essentially two parabolas joined back to back. Each orbit has a characteristic total energy. If the orbit is not a perfect circle (which it rarely is) potential energy is exchanged for kinetic energy and vice versa and the orbit bobs up and down during each orbit leading to an ellipse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/images/posts/saving-matt-damon/orbit1.png&quot; alt=&quot;An orbit.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other important variable that characterizes an orbit is the orbital inclination. Imagine a plane passing through the equator. The angle the orbit makes with this plane is called the inclination. A &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;0^0&lt;/script&gt; inclination means the orbiting spacecraft is always above the equator. A &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;90^{0}&lt;/script&gt; inclination on the other hand means that the orbit passes directly above the poles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s describe the rocket engine. A rocket engine works on the basis of Newton’s third law, that every action has an equal and opposite reaction. The simplest mathematical model of a rocket assumes that we throw of little pebbles in the other direction from which we want to travel; at regular intervals and obviously very fast. Each little pebbles has a mass and therefore gives a little kick to the rocket in the direction we want to travel. This “kick” is equal and opposite to the force we threw the pebble with. But the rocket doesn’t fly as fast as the pebble because it is much more massive. This is a more effective way than the rocket growing two hands and pushing itself off. Of course the rocket could just grow wings while at it although the atmosphere is too thin for wings where the rocket wants to go. (Aside: perhaps Icarus and his son did grow wax wings but the atmosphere was too thin that high up and also there was ice growing on the wings because it was so cold up there.) In a rocket engine the role of the pebble is played by the gas formed by the combustion of rocket fuel. Each gas molecule acts as a little pebble and the kick given by all the gas molecules is called the thrust. The variables that characterize the rocket engine are the effective exhaust velocity of the gas, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_{e}&lt;/script&gt; and the mass flow rate which is just the rate at which the fuel is used up. Both these variables determine the specific impulse of the rocket engine or the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I_{sp}&lt;/script&gt;. The &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I_{sp}&lt;/script&gt; is a measure of the overall efficiency of an engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://mentallandscape.com/V_RD253b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cut away of a closed cycle rocket engine.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of the above strategy for lift off gives us a neat little equation called the Tsiolkovsky Rocket Equation (TRE). This equation is exact for the model given above. In fact you need to assume only that to get this equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[
	\Delta v = v_{e}\cdot ln\left ( \frac{m_0}{m_i} \right ) 
\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please don’t have a panic attack! Ignore everything else and just focus on the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt; (say delta vee). The &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt; is just the change in velocity. So if you’re just starting out with a given amount of fuel and the provided rocket you can achieve a speed of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt;. If you’re at a certain speed v then you can achieve a speed of v + &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt;. Rocket scientist always talk in terms of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt; and not distance. To get off the earth and into orbit requires a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt; of v&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;. Escaping from Earths gravitational pull requires another &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt;, call it v&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. Slowing down on reaching Mars requires a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt; of v&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. Add that all together and you get a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt; of v&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; + v&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; + v&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. So the rocket scientist then presumably goes out into his backyard and choses a rocket that can deliver a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt; of just that. The good thing with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt; is that it’s relatively independent of the rocket’s design. Instead just tell the TRE the power of the engine and how much crew, food and fuel you’re hauling and it chucks out the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt;. At least if does so in theory. You actually have to be &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt; to be crazy enough to do that sort of stuff in real life. Interestingly, you don’t need a rocket to use the TRE. Farting in space is theoretically governed by this equation, although we can’t vouch for the after effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/sites/default/files/konstantin-tsiolkovsky.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tsiolkovsky&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The T in TRE stands for Tsiolkovsky, Constantine Tsiolkovsky. He was a Russian school teacher who derived this equation for the first time&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. He also suggested that a rocket engine might work in the vacuum of space and conjectured that a space suit might be required. The guy also figured out that getting a rocket to orbit and doing it in one piece is nearly impossible. The easier way is to jettison stage after stage till you’re in orbit. You see, most of the mass of the rocket is in the fuselage and the fuel. Each kilogram of fuel practically has to carry the mass of fuel tank require to carry itself and the previous kilogram of fuel and all the rest of the kilogram that came before. A better way is to just cut off that extra mass after a certain period of time. The answer is staging. Most American rockets have three stages. Some like the Ariane 5 has just two. But Soviet rockets had lots of stages. During the space race &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt; decided to build more powerful rocket engines and cut down the number of stages. The Soviets on the other hand had smaller engines but had more of them packed in smaller stages. An alternative to staging is called clustering&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which was also described by Tsiolkovsky. If you’ve seen pictures of old Soviet rockets like the R-7 and the Molniia then you’ve seen clustering. The four rocket engines surrounding the rocket core pivot outwards and detaches after their fuel has been depleted. This was necessary so that rocket engine would not have to be ignited in space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Hermes, the spaceship that carries Matt Damon and the crew of Aries 3 to Mars is built in orbit by launching smaller parts called modules in rockets and assembling it in orbit like we built the International Space Station. Launching a rocket means that it needs to go into an orbit. But keep in mind that in an orbit a spacecraft goes around in a elliptical path. In a perfect world we would launch the rocket right at the horizon to maximize efficiency. But due to friction with the atmosphere its more economical and fuel efficient to launch the rocket straight up for the first few minutes and then slowly tilt it so that ultimately the rocket follows a curve up into orbit. The reason is that in the lower atmosphere the air is very dense. So if you go sideways you’ll spend more time in the lower atmosphere and lose a lot of velocity. Instead following a curved path that is optimized by rocket scientists gets you the best of both worlds. The morale is to spend as little fuel as possible stuck in the atmosphere. Little is relative. A spacecraft spends most of its fuel just to get out of the atmosphere and in to orbit. A rocket never needs to spend as much &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt; as during launch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second procedure after launch is called the apogee burn. When you have gotten out of the atmosphere, you’re coasting along with engines shut in a parabolic path that will ultimately have you crashing down into the sea somewhere. But along this parabolic path there’s a point where the altitude of the spacecraft above the surface of the earth is maximum called the apogee of your orbit. Firing your engine along the direction of travel at this point (or doing a prograde burn as it is called) causes the parabola shape of your orbit to transform into an ellipse just above the atmosphere. With this burn you’re officially in orbit and if you’re a &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt; astronaut you’ll get a badge that informs you of this&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. At about an altitude of a 160km or so above the Earth’s surface an orbit would last a day or two before decaying. That’s why a rocket in LEO (Low Earth Orbit) needs to fire its thrusters now and then to maintain orbit. But an orbit above 600km or so is fairly safe from atmospheric drag forces and can spend a couple of years safely there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third procedure is docking. Getting a satellite into orbit is easy. But getting two spacecraft into orbit and making them connect to each other? Not so easy. In fact it required two tries for &lt;strong class=&quot;all-caps&quot;&gt;Nasa&lt;/strong&gt; to get it right. The first docking in space was done during the Gemini missions when Gemini 6A and Gemini 7 connected in space. The main point here is to launch when the target (which gets launched first) is right above your head. Getting into a close enough orbit that is a tiny bit lower than the target gets you closer to the target space craft as a lower orbit means a higher velocity. A higher orbit on the other hand takes you away from the target since you’re now moving slower compared to the target. Doing pointed burns gets the spacecraft closer and closer till you’re moving towards the target. The relative velocity is measured along the axis that passes through the target and your spacecraft. Space crafts are very fragile and at this point instead of the main engine the space craft uses its attitude jets which are gas jets powered by monopropellants like hydrazine. They are always fired pointed away from the target to prevent damage to the solar sails of the target. Then the two spacecrafts are docked together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Hermes has been loaded and fully fueled the next phase is to escape from the Earths gravitational pull. At the designated spot on the orbit firing the engines will cause the orbit to rise until the space craft achieves escape velocity which for the earth is 11 km/s. This is called a Hohmann transfer. A transfer orbit to Mars is feasible every 25 months&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Once the space craft drifts away from earth it is technically orbiting the sun. A few minor course correction will send it towards the Mars intercept point. Once there Mars will catch the Hermes in its gravity well. But here’s the catch. The Hermes will not be in a full orbit but in an orbit know as a hyperbola. Just like the parabola sends the spacecraft crashing down to earth and the ellipse sets it in a stable orbit the hyperbolic trajectory takes the Hermes into Mars orbit and then again away from Mars. In essence it’s called a flyby. But the Hermes needs to be in orbit to land on Mars. So we slow down by burning against the direction of travel (called a retrograde burn) and lowering the energy of the orbit so that an elliptical orbit is formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/basics/bsf16-20.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Leaving Earth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan to save Mark Whitney in the movie called Project Elrond requires the Hermes not to enter Earth orbit. Instead after a resupply run the spaceship flies by the earth and slingshots around the Earth to travel to Mars again. Slingshots around planet is a very fuel efficient way to travel the solar system although rather slow. The basic principle is that allowing the planet to capture the spacecraft in a hyperbolic orbit and then allowing it to leave, accelerates the spacecraft. In fact the spacecraft steals angular momentum from the planet. It’s an easy way to gain much needed &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta v&lt;/script&gt;. Voyager 2 was initally put in a Hohmann transfer orbit to Jupiter. A slingshot around Jupiter sent it to Saturn. At Saturn another slingshot sent it to Uranus.  The general term is for this is a gravity assist. In fact, theoretical calculations &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; show that slingshots around a gravitational system of three bodies configured in a precise way can accelerate a fourth body to near the speed of light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/basics/vtraj.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Path of Voyager 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after getting to Mars the Hermes does not go into orbit. Instead Matt Damon comes up in the MAV in parabola so that they meet at a certain point where Commander Lewis does an EVA to rescue him. There is a reason why the relative velocity must be small. Docking with a space craft is a perfect example of an inelastic collision. During the collision, Lewis’s and Damon’s orbits merge into a new one according to the law of conservation of momentum. In fact after that both Lewis and Damon would drift away from the Hermes if it weren’t for their tether. Since the Hermes is so large the collision changes its momentum very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;well&quot;&gt;Just on the aside, another curious use of a planet to save fuel involves something called aerobraking. The space craft in question, the Hermes, would plot a course where it would not just orbit the planet but would actually skim the upper surface of the atmosphere. If done right this would shave off considerable velocity due to friction with the atmosphere and change the hyperbolic trajectory into a perfect orbit. Of course, course corrections might be necessary. In fact I think this is what the Hermes really did before the beginning of the movie. Aerobraking using the Martian atmosphere so as to save fuel. You&#39;ll notice that the spaceship is more streamline than it needs to be in space. Although it could be because putting everything on a single line makes the Hermes much more maneuverable.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final question is, was Matt Damon worth saving? Was risking a billion dollar spaceship and the life of five people for a single man’s life worth it? I think it is. Humanity needs heroes to inspire us. To fight the fight we cannot fight. To go where we cannot go. If Matt was not saved then we practically allowed the man to die. And the best thing about humanity is that we never leave a man behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a side note, Hermes is the messenger to the Gods and especially close to Ares in Greek mythos. Ares is the God of war and later the Romans adopted him as their God, Mars. So yeah, who better to rescue a stranded Martian than Mars best buddy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;well&quot;&gt;I really liked the way music was used in the movie. It also features two of the best montages I&#39;ve seen since Rocky came out. I&#39;ve still got the lines to Bowie&#39;s Starman stuck in my head. Like Commander Lewis, I confess that I&#39;m a big ABBA fan but Waterloo is definitely not my favorite ABBA track. I like it first when I heard it but hear it twice and it gets irritating. Waterloo and Ring Ring are enough to drive anybody nuts. Waterloo was first featured in the Eurosong contest in 1974 and subsequently went on to become the ABBA&#39;s first hit song.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-divider&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Credit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image Credit Nasa, 20th Century Fox and Don P. Mitchell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;http://www.popsci.com/3-d-printed-tools-space &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See Rocket Propulsion Elements, George P. Sutton. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Status of Monopropellant Hydrazine Technology, T.W. Price &amp;amp; D.D. Evans. Find it on Amazon &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Status-Monopropellant-Hydrazine-Technology-Price/dp/B00CLJ916C&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.nasa.gov/audience/foreducators/rocketry/home/konstantin-tsiolkovsky.html &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;http://mentallandscape.com/V_LaunchVehicles.htm &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In fact you don’t need to go into orbit to get an Astronaut’s Wings. Just get 92.5km up in the sky. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/basics/bsf4-1.php &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See issue of Pi in the Sky Magazine. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/science-behind-saving-matt-damon/&quot;&gt;The Science Behind Saving Matt Damon&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on February 27, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chap.2 - Where to?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/stories/rosin-pt-2/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/stories/rosin-pt-2</id>
  <published>2016-02-25T12:20:28+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-25T12:20:28+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dcap&quot;&gt;“T&lt;/span&gt;he worlds gotten smaller,” the old man complained, barely able to sit up. Wheezes and coughs. “What happened to all the people?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re dead. Fermund thought. The plague took them. By not the old man. The chills would be the death of him alright. He gets up and walks outside. To breath the fresh night air, he tells himself. To run away, someone else says. In De**yuk he is a corn farmer and owns eighty parcels of fine land besides the river Feuyor - the watery saint of the plains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fermund! Where the fuck are you?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He signed. “I’m here pa. I’ll come in a minute.” He did not intend to. The moon was a slim crescent and on the wane. But the stars were out in great numbers. He walked down to stables. Melow was in her stall. She was two luminous orbs in an ocean of darkness. “You like me, don’t you girl. You’re the only one now.” He left the horse to herself and climbed up the hill, to the very top where he’d left a blanket and wood for fire. The fire crackled into life before him. Fire was warmth and he was starved for it. If fire was warmth then the kettle was a fiery blaze. He took a swing and another. Cyrus was rising. The stallion was high above at zenith. A westerly wind was blowing in promise of a cool night. One last swing of the canteen and he was content. He forgot the old man, his father. He forgot the corn that lay below him, waving wistfully in the moonlight. He forgot who he was and who he had been. There was only the future or a dream of it anyway. He loved this land. He knew every inch of her, the rock, the brook and stream. He loved his animals, especially Melow, the cows and his dogs. Giving it up would be hard. Harder than when Collie had died. Harder even than when he’d lost his mother. Yet give it up he would come the dawn. The plague had taken his village. The old man and he were the only survivors. They’d locked themselves up. Set the dogs on strangers. Boiled their water. Ate their seed when it came to that. They were truly alone now. The market where he’d sold his corn was gone. For ten years he’d grown corn out of habit. He had every thing he needed. Corn to eat. Water to drink. Surely a dog needed that but certainly not a man. He knew there were cities out west and people too. He would go there. Where ever there was people there was hope to be had. Cyrus was now at the zenith. The hunter was rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old man was gone. He’d thought so yesterday. He buried him besides Collie and his mother. Said the words and it was all over. A hundred miles of open country was his domain. He waited one more day. The corn would go to the birds like last year and the year before. Journey the dog would follow him. He set all the other animals loose. Let out the duck and set the fish free into the Feuyor. He broke the dam across the stream. He hitched Melow and Corinth to the cart and loaded it up with food,corn, lamp oil, hide and other things he could sell. The journey would be a long one – a hundred miles or so to Summerhills. “Journey! Come here boy. We’re leaving.” Journey ran up to him and placed his nose against his palm and licked it. “We have to leave now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was midday and spring had overstayed. The days were longer and winter was fast approaching. Melow and Corinth set a fast pace and the huge wooden wheels rattled over sand and gravel. Fermund rattled in his seat. Journey ran on alongside, poking his nose into a rabbit warren now and then, chasing a scrawny cat and having a good time. Sometimes he ran across the path of the cart, frightening the horses and he would have to shout at him. There was scarcely a cloud to be seen. Fermund felt lazy and at ease. He did not look back. Not once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;Dear Reader, this is the second chapter in a story that I&#39;m writing. You can find the rest of the story &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/tags/#rosin&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/stories/rosin-pt-2/&quot;&gt;Chap.2 - Where to?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on February 25, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Those Wordpress Days]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/blogging-using-jekyll/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/blogging-using-jekyll</id>
  <published>2016-02-23T11:30:24+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-23T11:30:24+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dcap&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;his blog is hosted on Github using Jekyll. I’ve blogged before using Wordpress and Ghost but never have I experienced such freedom as Jekyll offers. A long, long time ago I started a Wordpress blog at &lt;a href=&quot;https://000webhost.com&quot;&gt;000webhost&lt;/a&gt;. I was just a script kiddie then – a n00b – and was innocent and dumb to the dishonesty of the web. Like most users I was drawn in by these tempting words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;central-quote&quot;&gt;
000webhost.com ($0.00 webhost), is an industry leader in providing top class free web hosting services without advertising! There are no hidden costs, no adverts, and no restrictive terms. Lightning fast speeds, maximum reliability and fanatical user support are just a few of the features you&#39;ll receive with our service.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the fool I am, I believed them and signed up for a free website. Everything went well for a few weeks. Then almost imperceptibly my website began to load slower and slower until one day it took nearly a minute to load. A week later I was told I had used up all the bandwidth allocated to me and so my website would be put in cold storage until the next month. The inexplicable thing was that I had been promised a 100GB of free web traffic a month. I was a fledgling website and I had not even had a hundred visitors that month. On average each of my web page was less than a kilobyte in size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began looking for other offers of free web hosting. Lest my readers thing I’m a commie who expects everything for free, let me clarify that I had only the most noblest of intentions. I wanted to build a little blog and write some little things and code some little codes that would do little things. Was that too much?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next part of my saga led me to a web hosting provider called &lt;a href=&quot;http://wink.ws/&quot;&gt;Wink&lt;/a&gt;. Although I got what I wanted and more importantly, for free I was unsatisfied. You see, their control panel was cheesy and sucked. After having learnt my lesson I looked around for a cheap paid web hoster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around that time I was learning a new programming language called Ruby. I fell in love with it and was absolutely stolen by how intuitive it was. The code was beautiful and sophisticated. I also switched to Linux and started using the terminal by this time. Unknown to myself, I was metamorphosing into a serious web developer – a code junky. After mastering the basics of Ruby I decide to graduate myself and learn Ruby on Rails. Ruby’s uptown cousin on the web. I was told by the good doctor that I had two choices – deploy my code on Heroku’s world class infrastructure for free or deploy on Redhat’s open source Openshift web platform for not a penny paid. A tough choice. I chose Redhat over Heroku for reasons I could not comprehend. It turned out to be a good decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use Openshift I had to learn Git and was introduced to Github for the first time. I was immediately blown away by the sheer force of personality. To think there was an entire community of code loving geniuses hiding away their code on the web like so many acorn loving cartoon squirrels! I was in seventh heaven. Here finally was my promised land. I was introduced to Github pages and how I could deploy my webpage there. &lt;em&gt;Deploy&lt;/em&gt; not &lt;em&gt;Host&lt;/em&gt;! Deploy seemed to me a nice change from the arid sandy waste into which I had been cast. I learned about the Ghost blogging platform and flirted with her on Openshift before finally chancing on Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I look back I often wonder why I had not settled down with Jekyll before. To be sure I knew about Jekyll before but I always looked down on it as the unpolished cousin of Wordpess and other CMSes. How wrong I was! In fact it was the other way around. Wordpress had defiled blogging by making too many themes and plugins while separating the heart from the soul. While Jekyll was so different: powerful, yet elegantly usable. I was introduced to sass, the liquid templating language and yaml. I even built a theme for Jekyll of which I was sufficiently proud. And in the end I build this – the stuff you’re reading. I was one hell of a journey but worth each and every moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-divider&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/blog/blogging-using-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Those Wordpress Days&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on February 23, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chap.1 - The Plague in Valkaerd]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/stories/rosin-pt-1/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/stories/rosin-pt-1</id>
  <published>2016-02-22T12:49:47+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-22T12:49:47+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dcap&quot;&gt;I&lt;/span&gt;n the first year, nobody took notice. Seven people died that year. Each unknown to everyone else. Seven dead bodies amidst a dozen others. What was there to know? Summer hills killed a thousand each year. It was that kind of city. They were found floating in the canals, face down in their beds and mostly just laying by the way side. Yes, Summerhills could do that to you. A city has little pity being made up of people who have too much of that. Why that’s so I don’t know. Anyway, they were found dead. Seven dead men. No one thought much of it although the under taker would have told you there were blisters all over their skin. It starts as an itching. Then it puffs up and blisters. You wake up one night and find out your sheets covered in blood like there’d been murder done and hid. The fever starts in two days. You turn over in your sleep starts mumbling. Then the chills set in and you shake all the more.  It starts down inside of you and quickly builds up until the kings own fire cannot keep you warm. Death comes knocking in the morning. The undertaker follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven dead in the first year. Seven times seven the next year. Still not too bad. They drown twice. Once in dilerium and the second time in figures. The wheel once started rolls of its own will now. Four hundred and counting. The who’s who of the estaical court takes notice. Sends a man. The man dies within a week. The disease is now virulent. Death spawns death. Only this time three to one. Three thousand people dead another five hundred near death. Several thousand vulnerable. There are only so many concotions one can prescribe. There is mass panic. Of course there is mass panic. People flee to their family or relatives elsewhere. Four thousand dead and the rumour mongers get to work melting down facts and beating them down into shape. The devil, king and country are blamed one after the other. Like anyone of them cared. It’s God’s wrath delivered. For past service rendered. The figures climbs. Somewhere something happens. Critical mass is achieved. Exponential growth starts. Hey, if you fold a piece of paper again and again fifty times you’d reach the moon. You would if you weren’t so busy dying. But you do go to heaven. Again for past service rendered. Thirty thousand dead. That a quarter the population of Summer hills. Now the creepers taken root it can begin creeping. The refugees help a lot. Entire country side decimated. Women and children dead. Famine take the lucky ones. Indeed. Shocking. Eighty thousand dead. Did I mention the kings dead? Of bubonic plague of all things. A hundred thousand. Two hundred thousand. As auctions go they were widely successful. Three quarter the population wiped out in five years. The plague has run its course. The lessons learnt. Never empty your chamberpots in the streets. The Gods will take offence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s something brewing in the land. In the north the ice mountains have receded opening up much needed trading routes. In the south a duel is fought, half naked and in the sands. To the victor goes half a kingdom and glory. Between them the land of Valkaerd is open for business. The plague is ten years buried, to be dug up when the land returns to sea. Summerhills is no longer a large city. The survivors are happy though. Gjorg Pike makes a speech and shakes some spears and more spears start shaking for him. In a few years he is crowned chief. That is how you make a city states. Elsewhere more chiefs are made until finally there are seven. They hold council and peace is made. The dead are buried or rotted through or both at once. The survivors know the future is theirs. All great things begin with sorrow. But will it end with sorrow too?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-divider&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dcap&quot;&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;yda Cardus is six years old. Her father is arguing with someone. Ten years later she can’t remember his name. For her he was daddy. Someone who took care of you and loved you unconditionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The gates are closed. I can’t let you out. Can’t you see all of these people. Now shove off”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyda tugged at her father’s sleeve, “What’s wrong Dada?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The street is slick with the mornings rain. A crowd has gathered near the East gate porticus crying and shouting to be let out. An angry crowd is no place for a six year old. Her father moves with her into an alcove in the wall. She hides begins a statue of a man astride a horse in the alcove with her. Sword drawn and brandished in the air. Also slick with wet and cold to the touch. The air is feverish despite the rain. The crowd gathers and wanders, pulsates like a single organism. The shouts ring out in the air. Rises and falls. Her father has a bag slung over his back. It contains all their worldly possessions. She does not remember what it contains. But hopes her wooden play things are inside as well. A covered cart drawn by two horses appears and makes its way between the angry crowd. Mounted guards with spears pushes a way through the crowd. Her father asks her to wait here and she sees him walk away and disappear into the crowd. He seems impossibly tall to her. Strong and tall. It is the last memory she has of him. The shouts grew intense. She remembered the precise moment when the dam broke. Heaven and hell met for a moment and broke in each others embrace. Hopes and dreams were put in the same pot and dashed against the ground. The crowd pulls this way and that. You obey. Woe to anyone who disobeys. She was safe in her alcove with a hero to protect her. Three days later she wound up abroad a ship with orphans like her. A last act of kindness from the old empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-divider&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;Dear Reader, this is the first chapter in a story that I&#39;m writing. You can find the rest of the story &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/tags/#rosin&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/stories/rosin-pt-1/&quot;&gt;Chap.1 - The Plague in Valkaerd&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on February 22, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[How big is your prime gap?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/math/prime-gap/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/math/prime-gap</id>
  <published>2016-02-22T08:52:07+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-22T08:52:07+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dcap&quot;&gt;P&lt;/span&gt;rime gaps are the difference between adjacent prime numbers. There is no function in n that can tell you what the $nth$ prime number is. But a lot can be infered from the properties of prime numbers. For example, all prime numbers except 2 are odd. Therefore the prime gaps must be even numbers. It was Euclid who provided this marvellous proof that there are an infinite number of prime numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Suppose to the contrary that there are only a finite number of prime numbers.
Therefore there must be a largest prime number, $p$. In that case $1 \times 2 \times 3 \cdots \times p + 1$ 
is either a prime bigger than $p$ or is divisibe by a prime bigger than $p$. 
In either case we have a contradiction. Ergo, reducto ad absurdum there is no greatest prime. 
Which implies there are an infinite number of prime numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what of the spacing between prime numbers? Is there two prime numbers that are separated by a space greater than a give integer? In effect we are asking whether there are a, say $k$, number of consecutive composite numbers. We see that $n!+2$, $n!+3$, …, $n!+n$ are $n-1$ consecutive composite numbers. So not only are there an infinite number of prime numbers, the gap between adjacent primes can be as large as necessary. That is, if you choose any integer $k$ then there are always two adjacent prime numbers that are separated by a gap larger than $k$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-divider&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/math/prime-gap/&quot;&gt;How big is your prime gap?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on February 22, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[In the very begining - Dedekind-Peano Axioms]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://therocketeers.github.io/math/dedekind-peano-axioms/" />
  <id>https://therocketeers.github.io/math/dedekind-peano-axioms</id>
  <published>2016-02-22T05:05:25+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-22T05:05:25+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>James Powell</name>
    <uri>https://therocketeers.github.io</uri>
    <email>jamespowell.auth@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dcap&quot;&gt;I&lt;/span&gt;n the begining were the axioms and the axioms were with Euclid. For a long time this was the case until western mathematics was reformulated again at the end of the [century] century. Let me introduce you to the Dedekind-Peano Axioms of Arithmetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-dedekind-peano-axioms1&quot;&gt;The Dedekind-Peano Axioms&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 is a number.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 isn’t the sucessor of any number.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sucessor of any number is a number.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No two numbers have the same sucessor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Postulate of Mathematical Induction) If a set contains 1, and if the successor of any number in the set also belongs to the set, then every number belongs to the set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;i-classfa-fa-right-hand-oi-source&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-right-hand-o&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Source&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Reuben Herseh, What is mathematics really? &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io/math/dedekind-peano-axioms/&quot;&gt;In the very begining - Dedekind-Peano Axioms&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by James Powell at &lt;a href=&quot;https://therocketeers.github.io&quot;&gt;The Heart's Rocketeers&lt;/a&gt; on February 22, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>